（ナルト）あんなヤツに
どうやって勝つんだ！？
How am I supposed to
beat that guy?
（モトイ）さぁな。
俺は　そこまで知らない。
Well that, I do not know.
タコのおっさんってば
ここで修業したんだったよな。
Octopops trained here too, right?
タコのおっさんに聞きゃあ…。
I can ask him…
No, he won't tell me.
いや…　教えてくれやしねえか。
あの態度だもんな。
Not with that attitude.
だろうな。
Probably not.
《タコのおっさんにも
闇の部分があったのかな？》
I wonder if Octopops had
a dark half too?
Hey, Mr. Motoi…
モトイのおっちゃん…。
Can you tell me
more about Octopops?
タコのおっさんのこと　もっと詳しく
教えてくんねえかな。
生い立ちとか
どんな性格だとか　いろいろ…。
Like how he grew up,
and his personality.
Maybe I can get some hints from that.
そんなかに
なんか　ヒントがあるかもしんねえ。
タコのおっさんと　俺との違い…。
Maybe I can figure out
the difference between us.
もしかしたら
気づくかもしれねえ。
If you're a Jinchuriki,
((モトイ：テメエも人柱力なら
その存在が→
you can imagine the kind of life
he's had to lead, can't you?!
どういう生き様を歩いてきたか
だいたい想像できんだろ！
ああ　できるってばよ。
だったら　俺のことだって→
I sure can!
And that dude should be able
to imagine what it's like for me!
(想像できるはずだろ
あのおっさん！))
I don't like talking about other people.
他人のことを　ペラペラしゃべるのは
好きじゃないんだが…。
ナルト…　お前は
ビーさんと同じ　人柱力だしな。
But Naruto, you're a Jinchuriki
just like Master Bee.
九尾を安定させるのも
世界平和に繋がる。
Being able to control the Nine Tails
has a direct effect on world peace.
いいだろう。
サンキューだってばよ！
I'll do it.
Thank you!
さっき　お前に言ったな。
I told you earlier…
同じ人柱力なら
どういう生き様を歩いてきたか→
Since you're also a Jinchuriki,
you can imagine
the kind of life he's had.
想像できるだろう　と。
想像どおりだ。
And it's just as you
would imagine…
大きな力は　恐れを生み
わだかまりを生んできた。
Formidable power breeds
fear and antagonism.
ビーさんは　里の者たちに→
Bee has always been shunned and
ずっと煙たがられ
嫌がられてきた。
considered a nuisance
by the villagers.
だが　ビーさんは落ちこむことも
グチを言うこともなかった。
But he never got depressed
or complained even once.
ただひたすらに明るく
いつも　周りをなごませていた。
He was always cheerful…
always trying to work
the people around him.
何より　人柱力としての自分を
恥じるどころか　自らをアピールし…。
More than anything,
instead of being ashamed
that he was a Jinchuriki,
he didn't hide that fact.
俺が思うに　誇りを持って
己を表現してきたように見えた。
To me, he seemed to
take pride in himself.
Yo.
なぜ　人柱力である己に
そこまで誇りを持てたか…。
The reason why he was able to
take pride in being a Jinchuriki…
それは　おそらく
兄…　雷影様のためだ。
was probably because of
his older brother, the Raikage.
人柱力というのは
裏切りがないよう→
From days past,
in order to prevent betrayal,
昔から　五影の兄弟や妻など→
Jinchuriki have commonly been
selected from close blood relations
近い血縁関係にある人物が
選ばれるのが常だ。
of the Five Kage like siblings,
or even spouses.
人柱力は
里長である影を守る力であり→
A Jinchuriki is a power used
to protect the Kage,
the head of the village.
影の力を誇示する存在でもある。
It is also a symbol of
the Kage's strength.
ビーさんは　雷影様のために→
I think Master Bee tried to be
a fine Jinchuriki
立派な人柱力であろうと
したんだろう。
for Lord Raikage's sake.
It's said that he mastered
his training
この真実の滝での修業すら
あっという間に成し遂げたそうだ。
at the Waterfall of Truth in no time.
俺は　そんなビーさんを
心の底から尊敬している。
I deeply respect
the kind of person Master Bee is.
雲隠れの英雄として見ている。
I consider him to be one of
the heroes of the Hidden Cloud.
（ヤマト）そこまで慕われる人柱力…。
Such a well-loved Jinchuriki.
すばらしい人ですね　ビーさんは。
そして　あなたも。
Master Bee must be quite a person.
And you too.
そうだ！　そんだったら
モトイのおっちゃんが→
I know!
Can you ask the Octopops for
training hints on my behalf, Motoi?
俺の代わりに　タコのおっさんに
頼んでくれってばよ。
修業のコツをさ。
それは…　できない。
I can't do that.
な…　なんでだよ！
Why not?!
俺に　そんな資格はない。
I have no right to request
such a thing.
俺は…
ビーさんを殺そうとした人間だ。
I once tried to kill Master Bee!
Killer Bee and Motoi
Why?! You just said
you respected Octopops.
なんで！？　タコのおっさんを→
尊敬してるって言ったじゃん…
さっき。
You seem to have a reason.
何か　わけありのようですね。
なんなんだってばよ！
So what is it?
これは懺悔だな。
This is a confession.
ビーさんと同じ　人柱力のお前なら
あの出来事について話せそうだ。
You're a Jinchuriki like Bee,
so I think it's okay to tell you
about that incident.
あの出来事って？
Incident?
あれは　３０年前のことだ。
This took place 30 years ago…
（モトイ）あの当時　人柱力の力は
まだ　八尾の力を→
Back then, the Jinchuriki's power
was not strong enough
to completely control the Eight Tails.
完璧に　コントロールできるような
ものではなかった。
八尾は　何度も暴走し
雲隠れを破壊していた。
The Eight Tails often went
on a rampage
and wreaked havoc
on the Hidden Cloud.
先代の三代目雷影たち　エリートは→
Every time that happened,
the Third Raikage,
the Kage at that time,
そのつど
八尾の暴走を止めていた。
and his elite staff would
stop the Eight Tails.
Listen! I want you to stop
the Eight Tails' movements.
((いいか。
お前たちで　八尾の動きを止めろ。
その間に　俺が
ヤツを封印の壺に閉じ込める。
While you're doing that,
I will imprison him in
a Sealing Urn.
（エー）わかった。
Understood.
Okay, get to it.
よし　かかれ！
うわ～っ！！
うわっ！
クソッ　封印術で錬金した鎖が…。
Damn it! The chain forged
from the Sealing Jutsu…
諦めるな！
我々が諦めれば　雲隠れは滅びる。
Don't give up!
If we give up, Hidden Cloud Village
will be destroyed.
よし　これで…。
All right, this should…
今だ！　抑え込め！
Now! Pin him down!
（八尾）ナメるな！　人間風情が！
Don't mess with me,
lowly humans!
ハーッ！！
(ハア…　ハア…　ハア…))
（モトイ）どうにか暴れるのを抑え→
They were somehow able to suppress
the Eight Tails' rampages
八尾を　いつもの封印の壺に
押し込んでいたが→
and shove him back into
the Sealing Urn.
そのたびに
多くの死者が出ていた。
But there were fatalities each time.
だが　リスクはあっても→
However, despite the risk,
it was crucial to control
the Eight Tails
他国とのパワーバランスを
有利に保つには→
in order to preserve
the power balance between nations.
八尾の力を
コントロールする必要がある。
人柱力の実験は続けられていた。
Experiments continued
with the Jinchuriki.
そして
多くの死傷者のうちの１人に…。
Among the many who died or
were injured…
俺の父親がいた。
was my father.
あなたは
ビーさんに父親を…　だから。
Master Bee killed your father.
That's why…
いや　違う。
No, that wasn't it.
ビーさんと俺は友達だった。
Master Bee and I
used to be friends.
父が亡くなったとき
俺たちは　まだ５歳だった。
We were only five years old
when my father died.
((ビー　やったね))
Bee, you did it!
父を殺した人柱力は→
The Jinchuriki that killed
my father died
八尾を抜き取られ
封印したときに死んだ。
when the Eight Tails was
extracted and sealed.
It was the previous Kage's
Jinchuriki.
先代の人柱力だ。
そして　その後すぐに　ビーさんが
八尾の人柱力として選ばれた。
Right after that,
Master Bee was chosen to be
the Eight Tails' Jinchuriki.
なら　なぜ
あなたは　ビーさんを殺そうと…。
So why did you try to kill Bee?
八尾をコントロールすることなど
できはしない。
There is no way to control
the Eight Tails.
また多くの犠牲者が出る。
There would be many more victims.
そう思っていた。
That's what I thought.
そして　だんだん
八尾への憎しみが増し→
My hatred towards
the Eight Tails grew.
子供ながらに　どうにかして
復讐してやりたいと→
I was just a kid,
but I kept thinking
about getting revenge.
思うようになっていた。
((アーイェー　オーイェー　ヨーヨーヨー　チェケラッチョ。
(ヨー　ヘイ　チェケラッチョ　チェケ！))
ビーさんは　いつも笑っていた。
Master Bee was always laughing.
何も知らずに
いつも笑っているビーさんが→
I started hating him
more and more
because it seemed like
he didn't care.
だんだん　憎くなった。
八尾への憎しみが→
My hatred of the Eight Tails
人柱力のビーさんへと
すり替わっていったんだ。
shifted to Master Bee,
his Jinchuriki.
俺は　ビーさんを殺せば
八尾も死ぬと思っていた。
I thought if I killed Master Bee,
the Eight Tails would also die.
俺は　ビーさんを後ろから襲った。
I attacked Master Bee from behind.
…が　失敗し　恐ろしくなって
その場から逃げた。
But I failed and
ran away scared.
そのとき　顔は隠していたが→
My face was masked,
ビーさんは
俺だと気づいたのかもしれない。
but Master Bee might
have guessed it was me.
それ以後　俺からビーさんに
話しかけなくなった。
After that, I stopped talking
to Master Bee.
そんなことがあって→
Even after all that,
なんで　そこまで
ビーさんを尊敬するように…。
how did you come to
respect Master Bee?
憎しみは
すぐに消えたわけじゃない。
My hatred didn't
disappear overnight.
その後も俺は　ずっとビーさんの後を
つけるように監視し続けていた。
For a long time,
I continued to stalk Master Bee
and kept an eye on him.
でも　俺だけじゃなかった。
But I wasn't the only one.
ビーさんは　何度も里の者たちから
疎まれ　嫌われてきた。
Master Bee was shunned
by the villagers and despised.
ずっとな…。
All the time.
((どっか行け！
目障りなんだよ！))
Get lost! You're disgusting!
（モトイ）政治のために
勝手に人柱力にされ→
Even though he was forced to become
a Jinchuriki because of politics,
里を守るために
存在しているにもかかわらず→
in order to protect the village,
里の者たちから阻害され続ける。
people still ostracized him.
((オーイエー！　ヨーヨーヨー　チェケラッチョ！
Oh yeah?
Yo yo yo, check it out, yo!
Hey, yo yo, hey c'mon, yo yo!!
ヘイ！　ヨーヨー　ヘイ　カモン
ヨーヨー　チェケラッチョ！
Check it out, yo!
Yo, hey, yo yo!
(ヨー　ヘイ　ヨーヨー！))
（モトイ）常人では耐え難い生き様だ。
Anyone else would have gone insane.
そのとき初めて
俺以上に苦しんでいるのは→
And for the first time…
I realized that
Master Bee's suffering
ビーさんだと気づいた。
was even greater than mine.
なぜ　我々に？
Why did you tell us?
本当は　ビーさんに
聞いてほしかったのかもしれん。
Truth be told, I'd rather have
Master Bee hear this,
ビーさんの代わりに
ナルトに話してしまったのは→
but I think I'm telling Naruto
because he is a fellow Jinchuriki.
同じ人柱力だからだろう。
だが　いつかは　本当のことを→
I know that I owe it to Bee to
tell him the truth some day.
ビーさんにも話さなければと
思っている。
でなければ　懺悔にはならない。
Otherwise, it wouldn't be
a confession.
ハハハ…　都合がいいヤツだぜ。
How convenient for him.
フフッ。
ナルト　どこ行くの？
Naruto, where are you going?
少し　ひとりにしてくれってばよ。
I need to be alone for a while!
((ほら　あの子よ。
It's that boy…
Remember, stay away from him!
いいか　近づくんじゃないぞ。
Go away!
あっち行け！
I believed in you!
You're a hero, Naruto!
信じてたぞ！
お前は英雄だ！　ナルト！
アハハハッ　ありがとう　ナルト！
Thank you, Naruto!
（我愛羅）俺は　里の危ない道具。
To them,
I am now a relic of the past
that is difficult to get rid of.
ヤツらにとって消し去りたい
過去の遺物だ。
Gaara is the Kazekage,
you know.
（テマリ）我愛羅は風影なんだぞ！
フン　生意気な口きいてんな！
この下っ端ども！
Don't be so disrespectful!
You're nothing but subordinates!
（マツリ）我愛羅様は　無口で　クールで
強くて　かっこよくて　エリートで！
Gaara is reserved, cool, strong,
handsome, an elite, and…
《タコのおっさんは
あんなに信頼されるようになった。
Octopops has earned so much trust.
我愛羅も風影になって→
And Gaara has become
the Kazekage,
working for the sake of his village
and gaining acceptance.
里のみんなのために頑張って
認められるようになった。
俺だって　イルカ先生や同期のみんな
それに…》
And me, I have Iruka Sensei
and my comrades and…
Why didn't you give them
your autograph at Ichiraku?
どうして一楽で
サインを書かなかった？
アイツら
急に手の平かえしたように→
They changed
their attitude pretty quick
and tried to get friendly
with you, huh?
お前に
なれなれしくしてきたもんな。
うっとうしいヤツらだったもんな。
They were disgusting, weren't they?
《誰だ　お前は？》
Who are you?
The villager treated us
like outcasts, but now…
里のヤツら
今までさんざん俺たちのことを→
のけ者にしてきたくせによ。
俺は　お前自身。
お前の心の底にある　お前自身だ。
I am the real you that exists
deep inside your heart.
I am the real you.
《俺自身…
そんなこと思ってもみなかった。
The real me.
I never even gave it a thought.
でも　心のどこかで　まだ…》
But somewhere deep inside,
I'm still…
It's true.
《確かに　里のみんなに
信じてもらえるなんて→
I'm still not confident that I have
everyone's trust in the village.
自信がねえよ…》
ナルトのヤツ　どこに？
Where did Naruto go?
まさか　何か…。
Don't tell me…
この島は極秘の場所だ。
敵などいるわけが…。
The location of this island
is top secret.
There's no way an enemy would…
（モトイ）うわ～っ！
今のは…。
That was old man Motoi.
モトイのおっちゃん！
うぅ…　クソ！
Damn it!
モトイのおっちゃん！
Old man Motoi !
ナルト！　フォーメーションＣでやるよ。
Naruto! We're going to go
with Formation C!
なんで…　なんでだよ！？
Why… Why?
ナルト！　何してる！？
Naruto! What are you doing?!
やめろ！　タコのおっさん！
Stop, Octopops!
モトイのおっちゃんは　本当に→
Old man Motoi really trusts you!
タコのおっさんのことを
信頼してんだ！
イカだ！　これは　タコじゃなくて　イカ！！
It's a squid!
That's not an octopus!
イカ…　えっ！？　タコじゃないの？
A squid? What?
It's not an octopus?
１　２　３　４　５…。
1, 2, 3, 4, 5…
数えなくていい！！
丸いのがタコで　三角がイカ！
You don't even have to count.
An octopus is round!
A squid is triangular!
なんだ…。
What?
I thought Motoi told
the truth to Octopops
てっきり　タコのおっさんに
本当のこと　話して→
モトイのおっちゃんが
怒られたのかと思った。
and he got mad at him.
心配になって
キミを追ってきたとたん→
We got worried and
went to look for you,
こいつに襲われたんだ。
but this thing started
attacking us.
さては　こいつ
前にやられた　イカだな。
Let's see, this is the squid
that attacked us earlier!
うぅ…　うわぁ！
Naruto! Save the talking for later!
ナルト！　話はあと。　すぐにやるよ！
わかった！
Let's do this!
Gotcha!
木遁　黙殺縛りの術！
Wood Style! Silent Strangle Jutsu!
モトイのおっちゃん
今　助けっからな！
Old man Motoi!
We're coming to get you!
♪ 「気持ちをあずける
命をたすける」
I'll tell you how I feel…
♪ 「その役　俺様　俺のヤク」
♪ 「俺様　八尾は　再度　登場」
♪ 「イカしたイカはサイドアウト　以下省略」
タコのおっさん！
ビー…。　なぜ　俺を助けた？
ん？
ビーさん　気づいてたんだろ？
俺は　アンタを…。
（モトイ）アンタを殺そうとした…。
それなのに！
う～ん…
そんなこと　あったっけ？
俺が覚えてるのは…。
♪ 「俺とモトイ　俺とモトイ
モトイといた俺　元いた時間」
♪ 「２人で一緒に修業
失敗しても楽勝　爆笑」
♪ 「笑い合って　友情を実感」
♪ 「モトイといた俺　元いた時間」
イェイ！
（美空）
皆様　お変わりございませんか？
美空ひばりです。
では最後まで　ごゆっくり→
お楽しみください。
（宮本）『木曜８時のコンサート
名曲！にっぽんの歌』。